上一次阅读时，我们讨论了什么是好的抽象数据
Last reading, we talked about what makes a good abstract data
键入。
type.
好的抽象数据的最终性质
And the final property of a good abstract data
我们想花很多时间讨论的类型，
type that we want to spend a lot of time talking about,
它应该保留自己的不变量。
is that it should preserve its own invariants.
那这是什么意思？
So what does that mean?
不变量是程序的一个属性
Well, an invariant is a property of a program that is always
对于每个可能的运行时状态为true
true for every possible runtime state
程序可以进入的。
that the program can get into.
易变性是一个重要的不变量
Mutability is one crucial invariant
我们已经看到了。
that we've already seen.
一旦你创建了一个不可变的对象，
Once you create an immutable object,
它在整个生命周期中始终代表相同的值
it always represents the same value for the entire lifetime
关于那个物体。
of that object.
不管这个计划经历了什么样的状态，
No matter what states the program goes through,
那个物体应该代表同样的东西。
that object should represent the same thing.
所以说ADT保留了它自己的不变量
So saying that an ADT preserves its own invariants
意味着ADT负责确保
means that the ADT is responsible for ensuring
它的不变量。
that its invariants hold.
它并不依赖于客户的良好行为。
It doesn't depend on good behavior from its clients.
现在当ADT保留它自己的不变量时，
Now when an ADT preserves its own invariants,
对代码进行推理要容易得多
reasoning about the code is much easier
例如，如果你能相信事实，
if you can count on the fact, for example,
一根弦永远不会改变。
that a string never changes.
当你调试使用字符串的代码时，
And when you're debugging code that uses strings,
你可以排除这个字符串
you can rule out the possibility that the string might
在你脚下改变了。
have changed under your feet.
当你试图为另一个ADT建立一个不变量时
When you're trying to establish an invariant for another ADT
使用字符串，你可以相信
that uses strings, you can count on the fact
绳子不会变。
that the string won't change.
与字符串类型相比
Contrast that with a string type that
保证只有当客户承诺
guarantees it will be immutable only if its clients promise
别碰它。
not to touch it.
那你就得检查密码里的所有地方
Then you'd have to check all the places in the code
其中字符串可用于确保客户端
where the string might be used to make sure that clients
都在信守承诺。
are upholding that promise.
我们先来谈谈不变性。
Let's start by talking about immutability.
我们将看到更多有趣的不变量
We'll see more interesting invariants
稍后阅读。
later in this reading.
但不变性是一个很好的开始，因为我们
But immutability is a good one to start with because we're
已经很熟悉了。
already familiar with it.
下面是一个具体的例子。
Here is a specific example.
这是一个不可变的抽象数据类型。
This is an immutable abstract data type.
它代表，应该代表，
It represents, supposed to represent,
推特上的推文。
a tweet from Twitter.
一条微博有三个属性。
And a tweet has three properties.
它的作者是一个字符串。
It has an author that's a string.
它有一个字符串的tweet文本。
It has the text of the tweet that's a string.
有时间发微博，
And it has the time that the tweet was sent,
我们会用日期来表示。
which we'll represent with a date.
这有一个单独的创建者操作，
And this has a single creator operation,
需要作者、文本和时间戳，
which takes that author, text, and timestamp,
把它打包成一个tweet对象。
and packages it up into a tweet object.
然后观察者的操作基本上是
And then the observer operations are basically
这些字段是公共的。
these fields, which are public.
所以你可以找到作者。
So you can get the author.
你可以收到短信。
You can get the text.
你可以得到时间戳。
And you can get the timestamp.
只需使用点作者、点文本和点时间戳。
Just by using dot author, dot text, and dot timestamp.
现在我们说我们希望它是不变的。
Now we said we wanted it to be immutable.
那么我们如何保证这些tweet
So how do we guarantee that these tweet
对象是不可变的？
objects are immutable?
一旦创建了tweet，它的作者、消息和日期永远不会
Once a tweet is created, it's author, message, and date never
改变。
change.
好吧，这里有很多对不变性的威胁。
Well, there's a bunch of threats to immutability here.
这不是一个设计得很好的数据类型
This is not a very well-designed data type
如果它想是不变的。
if it wants to be immutable.
对不变性的第一个威胁来自于
The first threat to immutability comes from the fact
客户端可以直接访问其字段。
that clients can directly access its fields.
实际上，他们必须直接访问它的字段
In fact, they have to directly access Its fields in order
找出它们是什么。
to find out what they are.
所以没有什么能真正阻止我们编写代码
So nothing is really stopping us from writing code
像这样——构造一个tweet对象
like this-- constructing a tweet object
然后直接重新指派tweet对象的作者
and then directly reassigning the author of that tweet object
给另一个作者。
to a different author.
这意味着tweet并不是真的一成不变的。
This means that the tweet is not really immutable.
这也是一个小例子，一个简单的例子，
This is also a trivial example, a simple example,
一个叫做表象暴露的概念
of an idea called representation exposure, which is
抽象数据类型的风险。
a risk to abstract data types.
意思是类之外的代码
Meaning that code outside the class
允许直接修改表示。
is allowed to modify the representation directly.
这样的重复曝光不仅威胁到不变量
Rep exposure like this threatens not only the invariants
抽象数据类型的
of the abstract data type, but also
代表独立性，我们讨论过
representation independence, which we talked about
在之前的阅读中。
in the previous reading.
换句话说，我们不能改变实现。
In other words, we can't change the implementation.
我们不能允许实现者使用不同的定义
We can't allow the implementer to use different definitions
在不影响所有客户机的情况下
for these fields without affecting all the clients that
直接访问这些字段。
are directly accessing those fields.
幸运的是，Java为我们提供了语言机制
Fortunately, Java gives us language mechanisms
以应对这种公关曝光。
to deal with this kind of rep exposure.
这些私有关键字表示
These private keywords indicate which
字段和方法只能访问
fields and methods are accessible only
在班里。
within the class.
而公众则指出
And the public ones indicate which
一个可以在课外使用。
ones are accessible outside of the class.
所以现在我们可以创建显式的观察者方法
So now we can create explicit observer methods
你可以得到作者和文本，
that allow you to get the author, and the text,
还有时间戳。
and the timestamp.
这就是客户可以使用的，
And that's what the client will be able to use,
但他们将无法使用这些私人领域。
but they won't be able to use these private fields.
最后一个关键字，我们也讨论过，
This final keyword, which we've also talked about,
也有助于保证
also helps by guaranteeing that the fields
在对象为
of this type of tweet can not be reassigned after the object is
构建。
constructed.
但这不是故事的结尾
But that's not the end of the story
因为代表还没被曝光。
because the rep is still exposed.
所以想想这个非常合理的客户
So think about this perfectly reasonable client
使用tweet的代码。
code that uses tweet.
所以它需要一条tweet t。
So it takes in a tweet t.
T指向这个tweet对象。
T points to this tweet object.
它会得到tweet的时间戳，它会记住
It gets the timestamp of that tweet, which remember
我们说过会有个约会。
we had said would be a date.
所以它得到了时间戳
So it gets that timestamp and puts
在局部变量d中。
that in a local variable d.
现在，注意d和时间戳都指向
And so now, note d and timestamp are both pointing
到同一个日期对象。
to the same date object.
然后我们要做的就是加一个
And then what we want to do is add one
到时间戳的小时数，并创建
to the hours of that timestamp, and create
一小时后的新推文，但有相同的文本。
a new tweet that is an hour later but has the same text.
所以就像转发一样。
So it's like retweeting it.
所以我们加上一个小时
So we add an hour to this date, and then we're
正在构造一个新的tweet对象，该对象未在此处显示。
constructing a new tweet object which isn't being shown here.
但问题是那个突变，那个设定的时间，
But the problem is that that mutation, that set hours,
更改与原始tweet相同的日期对象
changes this same date object that the original tweet
这取决于。
t was depending on.
Get timestamp返回引用
Get timestamp returns a reference
指向tweet t t dot引用的同一日期对象
to the same date object referenced by tweet t dot
时间戳。
timestamp.
T点时间戳和d，换句话说，这个箭头
T dot time stamp and d, in other words, this arrow
那个箭头，是同一个可变对象的别名。
and that arrow, are aliases to the same mutable object.
所以当那个日期对象被d点集小时改变时，
So when that date object is mutated by d dot set hours,
会影响时间戳t和tweet t中的日期
that affects the date in the timestamp t, and in the tweet t
同样，如快照图所示。
as well, as it shows in this snapshot diagram.
所以我们打破了这个tweet的不变性。
So we've broken the immutability invariant of this tweet.
我们实际上已经改变了时间戳
We've actually changed the timestamp
原来的微博。
of the original tweet.
最根本的问题是微博泄露出去了
The fundamental problem is that tweet leaked out
对其不变性所依赖的可变对象的引用
a reference to a mutable object that its immutability depended
打开。
on.
我们以这样一种方式揭露了这个代表
We exposed the rep in such a way that tweet
无法再保证其对象是不可变的。
can no longer guarantee that its objects are immutable.
完全合理的客户代码
And perfectly reasonable client code
以为它是无害的
that thought it would be harmless
创建了这个微妙的错误。
created this subtle bug.
现在我们讨论了这个，在某种意义上，
Now we talked about this, in some sense,
在我们讨论返回不可变对象之前
before when we talked about returning immutable objects
从一种方法。
from a method.
我们可以使用防御复制修补此代码。
We can patch this code by using defensive copying.
换句话说，复制可变对象
In other words, making a copy of a mutable object
以避免泄露对该代表的引用。
to avoid leaking out references to the rep.
所以这是做这件事的代码。
So here's the code that does it.
这将使用
This makes a new date object using
与该日期对象中的时间戳相同。
the same timestamp that happens to be in that date object.
许多可变类型通常都有一个复制构造函数。
Many mutable types often have a copy constructor.
换言之，它接受类型的一个实例
In other words, it takes one instance of the type
并产生一个相同的实例，
and produces an identical instance,
但有不同类型的参考。
but with a different reference of the type.
在这种情况下，日期的复制构造函数
In this case, date's copy constructor
有点奇怪，因为你
is a little bit weird, because you
必须首先获取以毫秒为单位测量的时间戳值
have to first get the timestamp value measured in milliseconds
从1970年1月1日起。
since January 1, 1970.
Stringbuilder的复制构造函数接受一个字符串。
Stringbuilder's copy constructor takes a string.
所以你必须把另一个stringbuilder变成一个string
So you have to turn the other stringbuilder into a string
才能从中创建第二个stringbuilder。
before you can create a second stringbuilder from it.
在Java中，有另一种方法可以复制一个名为
There is in Java another way to copy a mutable object called
克隆，某些类型支持，但并非所有类型都支持。
clone, which is supported by some types but not by all.
克隆人的方式有一些不幸的问题
There's some unfortunate problems with the way clone
在Java中工作。
works in Java.
如果你想了解更多，谷歌搜索吧，
If you want to learn more, Google for it,
或者看看乔希·布洛赫的书中的第11条，
or look at Item 11 in Josh Bloch's wonderful book,
“有效的Java。”
"Effective Java."
所以我们做了一些防御性的复制
So we've done some defensive copying
在get timestamp的返回值中，
in return value of get timestamp,
但我们还没有结束。
but we're not done yet.
这里仍然有一个代表曝光。
There's still a rep exposure here.
所以请考虑这个完全合理的客户机代码。
So consider this perfectly reasonable client code.
我们试着写一个方法
We've got-- trying to write a method that
将生成一个包含24条鼓舞人心的推文的列表。
is going to generate a list of 24 inspiring tweets.
今天每小时一个。
One for each hour of the day today.
所以它会生成一个数组列表。
So it makes an array list.
有个约会。
It gets a date.
默认情况下，这会给你今天的日期。
And by default, this is going to give you today's date.
然后从0到24，从0到23，
And then runs through the hours from 0 to 24, 0 to 23,
事实上。
actually.
每一个都会改变这个日期
And for each one, it changes this date
所以它的时间是我。
so that its hour is i.
然后用那个日期创建一个新的tweet，
And then it creates a new tweet with that date,
现在，同样的信息。
and for now, just the same message.
我们可能希望这是不同的灵感
We probably want this to be different inspirational
信息，但现在，我们只是
messages, but for now, we're just
要做24个相同的信息。
going to do 24 of the same message.
所以我们得到了一个包含24个tweet对象的数组列表。
So we end up with an array list of 24 tweet objects.
现在这里怎么了？
Now what's wrong here?
问题是每个tweet对象
Well the problem is that each of those tweet objects
现在指向同一日期对象。
is now pointing to the same date object.
我们在这里传入了这个日期对象，
We passed in this date object here,
我们只是在进行变异。
and we were just mutating it as we went along.
所有24个tweet对象同时结束，
All 24 tweet objects end up at the same time,
刚好是23点，我们结束的那个。
which happens to be hour 23, the one we finished with.
因此，tweet的不变性再次遭到了侵犯。
So again, the immutability of tweet has been violated.
我们构建了这些早期的tweets，
We constructed these earlier tweets,
希望他们在更早的时间，0，1和2，
intending them to be at the earlier time, 0, 1 and 2,
等等，但他们最后都
and so forth, but they all ended up
在事实发生后被改变。
being changed after the fact.
问题是这次约会
And the problem was that this date
我们路过的东西刚被放进去
object that we were passing in just got put
在tweet的表示中，
into the representation of the tweet,
即使上面还有化名
even though there were still aliases to it
由客户代码持有。
being held by the client code.
所以我们也可以通过明智的防御性复制来解决这个问题，
So we can fix this problem too by judicious defensive copying,
这次是在构造函数中。
this time in the constructor.
在我们储存时间戳之前，我们先复印一份。
Before we store that time stamp, we make a copy of it.
一般来说，为了避免这种重复暴露，
In general, to avoid these kinds of rep exposure,
你应该仔细检查参数类型
you should carefully inspect the argument types
并返回所有ADT操作的类型。
and return types of all your ADT operations.
如果其中任何一个是可变的，那么
If any of them are mutable, then make
确保您的实现不会存储或返回
sure your implementation doesn't store or return
直接引用其表示。
direct references to its representation.
因为这样做会产生这些类型的代表曝光。
Because doing that will create these kinds of rep exposure.
现在你可能会抱怨这似乎是浪费。
Now you may complain that this seems wasteful.
为什么我们要复制这些日期？
Why are we making all these copies of dates?
为什么我们不能解决这个问题
Why can't we just solve this problem
一份精心编写的说明书
with a carefully written specification that
比如说，打电话的人一定不能
says something like, caller must never
再次更改此日期对象？
mutate this date object again?
这种方法有时在没有
This approach is sometimes taken when there isn't
任何合理的选择。
any reasonable alternative.
例如，当可变对象
For example, when the mutable object
太大，无法有效地进行复制。
is too large to do copying efficiently.
但代价和你的能力
But the cost of this, and your ability
为了解释这个程序，以及你避免错误的能力，
to reason about the program, and your ability to avoid bugs,
是巨大的。
is enormous.
在没有令人信服的相反论据的情况下，
In the absence of compelling arguments to the contrary,
对于抽象数据类型来说，它几乎总是值得的
it's almost always worth it for an abstract data type
以保证其自身的不变量。
to guarantee its own invariants.
而预防rep暴露对这一点至关重要。
And preventing rep exposure is essential to that.
现在是解决这个问题的更好办法
Now an even better solution to this problem
就是使用不可变类型。
is to just use immutable types.
如果我们使用了一个不可变的数据对象，
If we had used an immutable data object,
就像Java时区日期时间而不是这个Java.util.date，
like Java timezone date-time instead of this Java.util.date,
那我们早就结束这一段了。
then we would have ended this section a long time ago.
再也不可能暴露在公众面前了。
No further rep exposure would have been possible.
这正是我们用弦得到的。
And that's exactly what we got with strings.
可变数据类型周围有不可变的包装器。
There are immutable wrappers around mutable data types.
Java集合类提供了有趣的折衷方案
The Java collections classes offer interesting compromise
为了这个。
to that.
我们讨论过集合不可修改列表，它
We've talked about collections unmodifiable list, which
获取一个列表并用一个
takes a list and wraps it with an object that
看起来像一个列表，但其变异器抛出异常。
looks like a list but whose mutators throw exceptions.
所以你可以用变异器构造一个列表
So you can construct a list using mutators
然后把它封在一个不可修改的包装里，
and then seal it up in an unmodifiable wrapper,
你会得到一个不可变的列表。
and you get an immutable list.
然后从观察者方法返回是安全的，
And then that's safe to return from the observer method,
例如。
for example.
缺点是在运行时会得到不变性，
Downside is you get immutability at runtime,
但不一定是在编译时。
but not necessarily at compile time.
所以如果你调用一个变异器，比如这个不可修改列表上的sort，
So if you call a mutator, like sort on this unmodifiable list,
Java不会警告你。
Java won't warn you.
你只会在运行时得到一个异常。
You'll just get an exception at runtime.
但那还是比什么都没有好。
But that's still better than nothing.
所以不可修改的列表映射和集合
So unmodifiable list maps and sets
可以是一个很好的方法来减少错误的风险。
can be a very good way to reduce the risk of bugs.